You haven't done any of your labs?
Your matches were all on lab days?
Really?
Oh, crap.
I gotta get a hold of Mr. Sasaki.
Damn it.
This was the last report you had to make up.
Oh, crap.
Don't worry.
Um, that's enough for today.
We did what we could.
Not a chance.
We need to get this done as soon as possible.
Let's do the experiment right now!
Huh?
But how, sir?
We'll get help from the After School Burners Club!
The Burners Club?
Hey, is Noguchi here?
Huh?
Wait, what's going on?
Right here.
What can I do for you?
Huh?
Noguchi, what exactly are you making?
We're making soap.
We'll sell it at the bazaar to raise funds for the club.
Huh.
You actually know how to make soap?
You bet I do!
Here, see for yourself!
Say hello to our newest spring mixture, Mugwort Chocolate Banana.
Ooh.
Ugh.
Ugh, I don't think that stuff is going to sell.
How rude!
Between the Mugwort's sterilizing component, the chocolate, and the fragrant banana, there's
no way any girl will be able to pass on this.
Ah, sorry about that.
Oh, plop, plop, plop.
Ah!
What do you think you're doing?
Be more careful!
That's our precious Mugwort oil and grapefruit juice!
Hmm?
Hang on.
This fragrance.
It's refreshing, isn't it?
I wonder what that nice smell is.
What is that?
Wow, good job!
That was great work!
Welcome to the After School Burners Club!
All right.
What can we help you with, Mr. Hayashida?
Oh no, I completely forgot why I was here!
Hmm?
I was hoping that you guys could help us out with Kiriyama's lab report.
See, due to certain circumstances, he has to work while still attending school, so he's
missed a lot of classes.
He could end up having to repeat a grade.
So, I want you to lend him a hand.
That's some explanation.
Uh, I could use your help.
Work and school?
You've got a tough kid.
You are a working student!
Fine.
If it's related to science, the After School Burners Club would be happy to help!
Yeah!
Oh, great.
Thank you, Noguchi.
You're a good guy in spite of how old you look.
Not again!
Thank you.
And you're lucky I'm a nice guy.
You won't get much hope when you're that blunt.
Yeah.
The members of the Burners Club were really nice, weren't they?
Looks like you made some friends.
You should join them.
But, it was a nice change.
You know, when I saw you back there laughing with all the other students, it was like watching
a baby bird's first flight.
Am I making sense so far?
Yeah, yeah, yeah, I see.
Oh.
Ha ha ha.
I'm making sense so far.
When there's a problem, and you aren't able to fix it by yourself, reach out for the help
of a friend.
And then you can face it together.
And overcome it.
Whenever somebody helps you out of a jam, you need to be there to help them, too.
There's nothing wrong with asking for help.
It's natural to lean on others sometimes.
Trust me, Ray.
That's what really counts.
You got it?
No matter how hopeless you may feel at times, there's help out there.
Rely on others.
Because if you don't, no one will rely on you either.
That made me think of Akari and the girls.
I'd been so focused on appreciating their kindness, that I never gave them a chance to
depend on me.
That's right.
I never gave them the chance.
Well, I think that should just about do it.
You can think about it on the train ride back home.
Go on.
It's Goto and Shimada's final match.
Well, don't you want to see it?
When I arrived at the hall, it was just a little past eight.
Don't tell me.
It's over.
But who?
Which one of them won?
Not at all.
It's over.
I see.
Shimada Eight Dan won the match.
I've seen this before.
The aftermath of a hard-won battle.
The one who realized he was defeated,
sorted out his feelings before the match was even finished.
But the one who won,
who had been pushing himself not to make a single mistake to the end,
couldn't stop.
That's why the winner is often tremendously exhausted,
right after a major match,
just like now.
So much so,
that they may not even be able to speak.
Congratulations.
Sir?
What the hell?
Why are you crying, kiddo?
I'm not crying.
I'm just so happy there's snot dripping from my eyes.
That's disgusting.
Here, wipe.
I'm sorry.
Pardon me for interrupting.
Care to comment on today's match?
So, Mr. Shimada,
how does it feel to have made it to the Shishio Tournament Finals?
It's kind of hard to be excited.
Huh?
What the?
I mean...
I'm sort of a mess now after qualifying to become the challenger.
I'm anxious about what's to come.
In fact,
this round was so draining,
does there have to be a next one?
I was barely able to defeat Goto,
and Soya is even more of a monster.
Shimada Eighth-Dan,
isn't that too honest?
Shimada Eighth-Dan?
The Yamagata Journal.
Well, you've come a long way.
I'm Izumida.
I'm working on an article.
About you.
Come now.
Show a little spirit.
Us old folks in your fan club back home all have our hopes up.
Yeah, that's right.
You're not only an instructor,
you're also a hero at our kid's shogi club.
Good luck.
I see.
Yeah, I guess you're right.
I gotta do this.
This qualifying match was yet another tough battle,
but I'm thrilled to be in the finals.
It's truly an honor.
Seven matches are left in the Shishio Tournament.
Realizing the hope he carried,
Mr. Shimada began to speak.
He was given the gentle push he needed.
One word at a time,
forcing each word out.
I wonder
if I've ever gone for a win like this,
as if jumping in head first.
I get it.
Mr. Shimada is somewhere far away from here,
in a world that I could never reach
without grave consequences.
While feeling like I had no reason to win,
and still wondering why it was so frustrating to lose,
I looked away from that world entirely.
And at the end of it,
Kiriyama!
Hey, good to see ya.
He moves forward,
pressing on alone,
as determined as ever.
Then all of a sudden,
I could feel my chest tightening,
and a strong rush of heat
filling the back of my throat.
Hey, kiddo.
Do me a favor
and find me something cold to drink.
Sure.
Is tea okay?
Yeah, thanks.
I may not have anything I can give him,
or anything he could use in exchange.
But there's...
something I need.
I just have to ask him.
Well, um...
Uh, Mr. Shimada?
About the workshop.
Please let me join.
Want to join?
Wait, how, how did you...
Sorry that took so long.
Uh, hey, um...
What's going on?
What happened while I was gone?
Why are you guys acting so funny?
Hey, come on!
Kiriyama!
Let me in on it, too!
Hey, no fear!
What's the status?
Ah!
No!
Close the door!
Be careful!
You're letting the cats in!
Sorry about that.
Uh, paper!
I want to run on the paper!
Here, take these.
They're ready.
Great!
Looks like we'll make it in time.
Now I'll be able to complete the addition to that order.
This is beautiful work, Hina.
Really.
Outstanding job!
It's wonderful that we're getting additional orders.
How nice!
It's a good thing we ordered a lot of boxes.
And Hina's idea was perfect.
Yeah, it was much cheaper to buy plain boxes.
And now that I've gotten used to stenciling,
I should be able to make even cuter prints.
Speaking of cute,
those girls' festival suites are adorable!
We sell so many of those multi-tiered boxes.
I'd be thrilled to get one myself.
All right, then.
What shall we do for the girls' festival at our house this year?
Inari sushi!
Hold on.
Isn't that Shirashi played a girls' festival standard?
Or egg-wrapped sushi?
Inari sushi!
Sounds good.
Now I want inari, too.
Hmm, sounds so good.
I guess that'd be okay.
Now I'm craving it, too.
Why don't we make a big plate full of them?
And let's make some clam soup to go with it.
How delicious.
What is it that makes Inari sushi so good?
Sweet deep-fried bean curd with crunchy lotus root,
powdered egg, and sesame seeds inside.
If we're not careful, we'll just end up eating them all.
Inari sushi!
Hurry up!
Mama wants to make them!
Let's do it!
Yeah, let's love them up with sesame seeds!
I wish we could share some of it with Ray, too.
I wonder how he's doing.
It'll probably take a little more time.
Kid or not, he's also a man.
He's got his pride, after all.
Just be patient.
That doesn't make sense!
I'm so confused!
Is it okay for him to go hungry in the name of pride?
Being hungry isn't going to make you happy!
If he doesn't want to come over to our house anymore, then fine.
I'll just go to his place,
and stuff his dumb mouth with seminari sushi!
I think it should be somewhere nearby.
I guess I'll try looking down here.
The house was in a really nice location.
On a hillside, in the old part of town.
Hey, glad you could make it.
I thought you might need to call.
It's hard finding anything around here.
Sorry for showing up so late.
It was my first day to join in Mr. Shimada's workshop.
Everyone meets at his place.
Hey! You're late, Kiriyama!
I'd heard about meetups like this before.
But this was my first time to participate in one.
And I was a little nervous.
Let me introduce you.
This is Morio Shigeta.
We've been buddies since joining the association around the same time.
He's a little quiet and tends to glare a bit,
but he's actually not as angry as he looks.
And, once he gets to know you,
he can be pretty sharp-tongued.
But don't let that bother you.
Except for Durin's shogi.
He never says more than like three things in an hour.
But don't let that fool you.
He still wants to be here.
Oh, hello there.
I'm happy to meet you.
Come on now, Shigeta.
This is Kiriyama.
You know about him.
Well, shall we get started?
The time limit will be one hour,
followed by a 30-second countdown.
After both of our games are over, we'll review them.
Sound good?
Yeah.
Yes.
Great.
Then let's play.
In a workshop,
four to six pro shogi players get together.
They meet about once a month to study the game
and practice together.
Each player gets 30 minutes to an hour of game time.
When their time is up,
they take a 30 to 60-second break.
It's common to play two or three games at each workshop.
After every game is over,
the members discuss their moves
and analyze their results.
By working together,
the players find new paths to success
on a familiar board,
utilizing the eyes of their fellow players
to gain new insights to the game.
A workshop is a place where you can test each other.
All right.
Now let's take a look at your matches.
Let's see.
Nikaido started with a static rook
and Shigeta followed with a cheerful central rook.
Yeah, that's right.
Out of the various ranging rooks,
using a cheerful central rook
is the most daring strategy.
That is if you want my opinion.
What exactly do you mean by that, Nikaido?
How do I put this?
The ranging rook is a passive counter move
with the aim being a long, drawn-out battle,
but I don't really see that
as being a gutsy move in the first place.
Oh, yeah?
Then I have something to say as well.
What about the static rook opening you used?
That does nothing at all
but show you're in the game for the long haul.
You started calling it
the boldest strategy of ranging rooks,
while failing to mention
I only played the cheerful central rook
to break your castle defense.
That's a rather petty way of looking at it.
Well, blocking the open bishop
is such a passive move,
I can't help but wonder what you were thinking.
It's like you stopped trying to win
and aimed only to play counter moves.
Okay, settle down now, settle down.
This argument could reach the ends of the Milky Way
without an outcome, right?
Shimada's right.
We should just move on.
So let's try to keep it friendly, okay?
Oh, thank you, Kiriyama!
And besides, neither tactic is that special.
They're both pretty basic.
What'd you just say?
I don't think I heard you right!
Pawn to 3-6, king to 7-2,
and here, probably silver to 3-7.
How totally foolish.
If you went silver to 3-7,
I'd go from silver 6-5 to pawn 5-6,
so don't even think about it.
Achoo!
Huh?
But if I went silver 3-7 instead of my right gold 5-8,
my other silver would take your knight
and I'd have control of the center.
That's right.
Kiriyama makes a good point.
But going old school with silver 4-7 to silver 3-6
is a more dignified approach in terms of the static rock.
Are you serious?
If you really believe that,
you'd better use that strategy in an actual game.
I mean it.
Use it next time,
even though you'll definitely lose.
Yeah, um, excuse me.
Sorry for interrupting when you're having such a lively discussion, but...
What?
Mind if I say something?
I hope he'll be okay.
I wonder what's wrong.
All of a sudden he said he had a bad stomach ache.
It's weird.
He's never under the weather.
He takes good care of himself,
so it's unusual for him to get sick all of a sudden.
I wonder what happened.
The title match is coming up.
Maybe he's feeling the pressure from that.
I hope he feels better before the finals.
But silver 4-7 to silver 3-6,
that's how it should go.
Man, you're stubborn.
You're still on that.
All I'm saying is that instead of from silver 3-7,
silver 4-7 stops whatever plans your opponent had.
And I'm saying there's no guarantee
your opponent will do what you want.
But still, silver 4-7 isn't wrong.
It's a great move to make in that situation.
Dammit.
If only we had a board with us right now,
I could show you that it would work just fine.
I've got an idea.
Let's go to your place and use your board to hash it out.
Hold on. Wait a minute.
Huh? I don't get it.
How did we both end up here outside my building?
You followed me home again,
and I never agreed to that.
Silver 4-6 to knight 3-7.
I would still go from silver 4-7 to silver 3-6.
Hasn't that bird been down there for a really long time?
It dove in a while ago.
That's crazy.
How long can a bird stay underwater?
Can they really hold their breath that long?
I don't know.
Scary.
Do you think a fish could eat it?
Look there.
They do have it.
It's right by the door.
Yes.
I knew a bookstore by the river would have it.
Must be a demand for it.
Oh no.
There are this many types of birds?
Which is the one we saw?
It's that one.
Don't be stupid.
The bird we saw was brown.
You'd know if you read it.
Its wingspan is approximately three and a half feet long.
The one we saw wasn't nearly that big.
All right.
We gotta get back to the riverside.
Then we'll know for sure.
Yeah.
I wonder what happened to it.
I'll get to the bottom of this damage.
I swear I'll figure out what it was.
Let's do it.
How's Kyoko been doing lately?
Thanks for your patience. It turns out he was in the garden.
Come inside already.
Nikaido's been impatiently waiting for you to finally get here.
I finally caught up to you, Kiriyama.
I'm looking forward to a squaring off.
It's gonna be epic.
You snitched on me to dad, didn't you?
Watch the next episode of March Comes In Like a Lion.
The kid's doing his best. Hot damn.
Hot damn.